<resources>
    <string name="app_name">॥ अष्टादशशक्तिपीठम् ॥</string>
    <string name="temple_one">Shankari Devi Temple</string>
    <string name="temple_two">Kamakshi Devi Temple</string>
    <string name="temple_three">Shri Srinkhala Devi Temple</string>
    <string name="temple_four">Chamundeshwari Devi Temple</string>
    <string name="temple_five">Jogulamba Devi Temple</string>
    <string name="temple_six">Bhramaramba Devi Temple</string>
    <string name="temple_seven">Mahalakshmi Devi Temple</string>
    <string name="temple_eight">Eka veerika Devi Temple</string>
    <string name="temple_nine">Mahakali Devi Temple</string>
    <string name="temple_ten">Puruthika Devi Temple</string>
    <string name="temple_eleven">Biraja Devi Temple</string>
    <string name="temple_twelve">Manikyamba  Devi Temple</string>
    <string name="temple_thirteen">Kamarupa Devi Temple</string>
    <string name="temple_fourteen">Madhaveshwari Devi Temple</string>
    <string name="temple_fifteen">Vaishnavi  Devi Temple</string>
    <string name="temple_sixteen">Sarvamangala   Devi Temple</string>
    <string name="temple_seventeen">Vishalakshi Devi Temple</string>
    <string name="temple_eighteen">Danteshwari Devi Temple</string>
    <string name="temple_nineteen">Saraswathi Devi Temple</string>


    <string name="text1"><![CDATA[
    Aadi Shankaracharya\’s Stotram starts with Shankari Devi Shakthi Peeth. Here Devi Sati’s groin had fallen. Sati Devi is worshipped as Shankari Devi and Lord Shiva as Trikoneshwara.

The temple is located in Trimkomali, or Trincomalee on the eastern coast of Sri Lanka. The place Trinconmalee means a triangular shaped hill (Tri- cona- malee or malai). The temple is well connected by roads. There is also a Kali temple which people visit enroute to Shankari Devi temple.

Many have heard the Ashtadasha Shakti Peetha Shloka starting with LANKAAYAAM SHAANKARI DEVI........... - composed by Sri Adi Shankara which means Shankari in Lanka. This Shloka enumerates the list of places of Devi temples which are considered to be part of the 18 Devi Peethas.

The Temple of Sri Shankari Devi according to the priests in Trincomalee, say that the Portuguese who invaded the island in the 17th century completely cannon balled from their ship and demolished the cliff top Devi temple. In its site stands a lone pillar, as a mute spectator.

The present Shiva temple which is quite well known locally than the Shankari Temple was a recent construction. The Shiva is called as TRIKONESHVARA (Probably because it is in Trincomalee which is truly TRI CONA MALAI- meaning triangle shaped hill).
]]>
</string>


    <string name="text2"><![CDATA[
    The town of Kanchi was the capital of the ancient Pallavas. The Kailasanathar temple here is one of the grand Pallava monuments. The Kamakshi Amman temple at Kanchipuram is an ancient one and is associated with Aadi Sankaracharya of the 1st millennium CE. The Tamil saying Kanchi Kamakshi, Madurai Meenakshi and Kaasi Visalakshi illustrates the importance of the Shakthi shrine that it is.

Legend has it that Kamakshi offered worship to a Shivalingam made out of sand, under a mango tree and gained Shivas hand in marriage.

It is believed that Kamakshi was originally a Ugra Swaroopini, and that Aadi Sankaracharya, upon establishing the Sri Chakra, personified her as the Shanta Swaroopini (see also Akhilandeswari at Tiruvanaikkaval). It is believed that during the days of Adi Sankara, the presence of the Ugra Swaroopini was felt outside the temple precincts, and that Sankaracharya had requested her not to leave the temple complex.

About Goddess Kamakshi: The Padmasana posture is said to resemble a lotus. In the Yogic practice this resembles the form of meditation. The Goddess holds a Sugarcane bow on her left upper arm and Lotus, Parrot in her right upper arm. The Goddess also has divine chakras called Pasa and Angusa in her arms. The Goddess also has a Chandraperai (a shape of moon like structure) in her forehead. The Goddess Kamakshi is situated in the middle of temple premises.
]]>
</string>


    <string name="text3"><![CDATA[
Shrinkala devi was supposed to be in West bengal, hoogly district.But as such there is no temple also.A story says that Sage Rishya Shringala has brought to her to shringeri in Karnataka

There is also a contest in great epic of hindus The Ramayana about this sage that he was the one who conducted the Putrakaameshti yaaga for king Dasaradha.
King Romapada a friend of Dasradha adopted Santha devi who was the sister of Sri Rama. He requested this sage to conduct a yagna to get relief of very long famine which was relieved after the yagna.On the request of the king this sage married Santha devi and conducted the above metioned Yagna .

After some time this great sage as was a great devotee of Shrinkhala devi brought her in the sense his mother to Sringeri and distributed the energy around the Srunga parvatha and there he constructed temples to the deity. These places are also regarded as Shakti peethas.
]]>
</string>


    <string name="text4"> <![CDATA[
        Mysore was ruled by the demon-king Mahishasura, he was a buffalo-headed monster. For this reason, came the name of this place - Mahishuru, the town of demon Mahisha. Hearing to the prayers of Gods and Goddess to save them from the monster, Goddess Parvathi, (consort of Lord Siva), took birth as Chamundeshwari and killed the monster. After killing the demon, the Goddess resided atop the Chamundi Hills, where she is worshiped with reverence and devotion. The goddess is also called Mahishasura Mardini meaning She who slew Mahishasura.


About the Temple : The Chamundi temple has always been patronised by the rulers of Mysore. In 1659 Dodda Devaraja Wodeyar built 1,000 steps and big Nandi, Lord Shivas Bull. This gigantic Nandi is likely one of the largest within India, 16 ft. (4.8 meters) tall in the front and 25 ft. (7.5 meters) in length. The magnificent pendent bells around its neckline are exquisite. Nandi as well as the temple beside it can be found at the 700th step of the Chamundi Hill.
]]>
</string>


    <string name="text5"><![CDATA[
        Jogulamba Devi temple at Alampur, one of the 18 Sakti peethams in Indian sub-continent, including Sankari Devi temple in Sri Lanka, has been reconstructed after 615 years. According to historical sources, the temple was razed to the ground during Muslim invasion in 1390 AD. The local people put up a fierce resistance and killed the invaders and moved the main idol to the nearby Balabrahmeswara temple. Since then, the idol had been worshipped in the secluded place in the temple.

History of Alampur
Alampur was under the rule of Shatavahana Ishvakus of Nagarjunakonda, Badami Chalukyas, Rashtrakutas, Kalyani Chalukyas, Kakatiyas, Vijayanagara Empire and Qutb Shahis of Golconda. Alampur was previously Known as Halampuram, Hamalapuram And Alampuram. Name of this place as Hatampura, mentioned in the inscription dated AD 1101 belongs to Western Chalukya, Tribhuvanamalla Vikramaditya VI. There are Navabhrama Temples, these impressive temples should be visited on tour to Andhra Pradesh not only because they are historically important but also because they reflect remarkable architectural skills.
]]>
    </string>


    <string name="text6"><![CDATA[
        The main temple of Bramarambha devi , first of Asthadasa maha sakthi peethas is with well sculptures. You can hear butterflys sound(Bhrama means butterfly) in the back side of the main temple. Devotes are not allowed inside the temple whereas in the Mallikarjuna swamy temple.


Srisailam is the spiritual station which contains 8 gateways in side and corners of Srisailam. Every inch of Srisailam surroundings is having its unique and sacredness. It clearly revealed in Puranas, inscriptions and other sources available in this area. It is very vast circumference, which contains thousands of temples, streams(Teerthas), portraits of Gods/ goddesses were stationed here. of all these some are dilapidated condition, some are demised and some are existed in these centuries course of time. Srisailam is in thick and dence forest of Nallamalla. Even today , most of the places are not able to reach due to not knowing of their where abouts and no formations of roads. Because of that devotees of lord Shiva are not able to visit these places.

]]>
    </string>


    <string name="text7"> <![CDATA[
        Kolhapur is located in Kolhapur district and is well connected with Pune, 240 km north. It is on the national highway between Bangalore and Pune. It is situated on the banks of the Panchganga river and is full of ancient temples and shrines. Goddess Mahalakshmi resides in Kolhapur, and is been a famous holy place right from ancient times pilgrims from far and near have continued to flock here in their thousands year after year. So great was indeed its repute that it was known as ’Dakshin Kashi,’ the Kashi of the south.

The four Shakti Peethas of Maharashtra are Tuljapur enshrining Bhavani, Kolhapur enshrining Mahalakshmi, Mahur enshrining Mahamaya Renukaand Saptshringi enshrining Jagadamba.

The image of the Goddess has an extremely pleasant appearance. It is carved in black stone, is about three feet in height and has four arms and crowned Goddess made of gemstone and weighs about 40 kilograms. It contains mater mixed with Hirak bits.. The typical ayudhas of the devi are as follows. In the lower right hand is the matulinga, a fruit not unlike the ordinary lemon, but much larger in size. In the upper right hand is a large mace, kaumodaks, and its head touching the ground. The upper left hand holds the shield or khetaka, the lower one holding a bowl i.e. panpatra.
]]>
    </string>


    <string name="text8"> <![CDATA[
        Ekaveerika devi temple is in Mahur , Maharashtra. The deity here is called Ekaveerika mata. The temple is in Yavatmal district in Maharashtra. It is 50 km from Kinwat and 126 km from Nanded. Nagpur is 210 km by road from Mahur. Sati\'s Right shoulder has fallen here.

Mahur is famous for Renuka Devi temple and very few people are knowing about Ekaveerika devi temple and mostly they call Renuka devi temple as shakti peeth. We find more rush at Renuka devi temple than Ekaveerika mata temple. It is said that Ekaveerika Devi is the elder sister of Renukadevi. Renuka devi temple is 800 years old.

Ekaveera mata temple : It is present on the bank of Pen Ganga river (Pancha Ganga river). It is about 30 to 40 minutes distance from Mahur. The temple is present in the fields of near by Village. The temple is very small. We will see only the head of Goddess here.

Renuka mata temple : Renuka mata temple is present on the top of Hill near Mahur. Renuka mata is the mother of Lord Parasurama. Jamadagni Maharshi, husband of Renuka mata is also present in the form of Shiva linga. The temple is present in deep forest and we can see Peacocks in the journey.

]]>
    </string>


    <string name="text9"> <![CDATA[
        Goddess Mahakali is also known as Rakt Dantika or Chamnuda. Mahakali appeared to kill the demon Andhakasur.

The Maha kali (hara sidhi mata) was the aradhana devi of The great King Vikramadithya. It is said that King Vikramadithya has offered his head (sirassu) by cutting 11 times to devi and all those times devi made him live by jointing it back. We will find his portrait a hall next to the temple.

The Maha kali (hara sidhi mata) was the aradhana devi of The great King Vikramadithya. It is said that King Vikramadithya has offered his head (sirassu) by cutting 11 times to devi and all those times devi made him live by jointing it back. We will find his portrait a hall next to the temple.

some of the important festivals celebrated at Ujjain Mahakali Shakti Peeth-

    Chaitra Navratri
    Ashwin Navratri
    Durga Puja
    Shivratri
    Magha Purnima
    Falguna Purnima
    Paush Purnima
    Shravan Month
    Maha Kumbh Mela
]]>
    </string>


    <string name="text10"> <![CDATA[
        Pithapuram is formerly called as Pithikapuram / Pushkara kshetram in Puranas and Tantras.
The temple of Puruhutika devi

Kukkuteswara swamy temple is present in the outskirts of the Pithapuram village towards Kakinada. It is a big temple. Just entering in to the temple we will see a pond which is called as Padagaya sarovaram (Pada Gaya Sarovar). Pilgrims will take holy bath in this pond. Main temple of Kukkuteswara swamy is present towards the right side of the pond. Puruhutika devi temple is present in the North-East corner of the Kukkuteswara swamy temple. It is constructed facing South. Puruhutha temple is small but looks very nice with the carvings of Ashtadasa Shakti peethas on its walls.

The idol of Puruhuthika devi has four hands. They contain bag of seeds (Beeja), axe (Parashu), lotus (Kamala) and a dish (Madhu patra) from lower-right to lower-left in order.
]]>
    </string>


    <string name="text11"> <![CDATA[
        The Biraja Temple, or Girija  is located in Jajpur (about 125 kilometres north of Bhubaneswar), Odisha, India. The present temple was built during the 13th century. The principal idol is Devi Durga, who is worshiped as Viraja (Girija), and the temple gave Jajpur the nicknames "Viraja Kshetra" and "Biraja Peetha".

The Durga idol has two hands (dwibhuja), spearing the chest of Mahishasura with one hand and pulling his tail with the other. One of her feet is on a lion, and the other is on Mahishasura\'s chest. Mahishasura is depicted as a water buffalo. The idol\'s crown features Ganesha, a crescent moon and a lingam. The temple covers a large area, and has several shrines to Shiva and other deities. According to the Skanda Purana it cleanses pilgrims, and it is called the Viraja or the Biraja kshetra. Jajpur is believed to have about one crore of Shiva lingams.
]]>
    </string>


    <string name="text12"><![CDATA[
        There are two stories related to Pancharama temples. One story related to Pancharama temples is in Bheemeshwara Puranam written by Shree Nathudu. The Story goes like this..

Devatas and Asuras (Rakshasas) stirr the sea to get nectar (Amrit). After getting the Amrit, Devatas meet Lord Vishnu to avoid distributing the nectar to Asuras as it may lead to problems. Lord Vishnu takes the birth as Mohini and distributes Amruth only to Devtas. Asuras get angry and worship Lord Shiva. Lord Shiva gets satisfied by their worship and blesses Asuras with lot of powers.

With these powers Asuras start torturing people and Devtas. Again Devtas worship Lord Shiva to avoid this. Lord Shiva gets angry and starts punishing Asuras. During this war, a Shivalingam worshipped by Thripurasura (Tripurasura) remains un damaged even though all Asuras die. Lord Shiva (Mahadeva) makes this Lingam into five pieces and makes this installed in five different places. These five places (Prathishtapana) are now famous as Pancharama.
]]>
    </string>


    <string name="text13"> <![CDATA[
        The shrine of the goddess Kamakhya is situated about three miles from the present town of Gauhati and about fifty miles from the range of hills inhabited by two aboriginal matriarchal tribes, the Khasis and the Garos, the former belonging to the Austro-Asiatic and the latter to the Mongolian stock.

The name of the hillock where the shrine stands is Nilachala (blue mountain). According to the K.P. the genital organ of Sati fell here when her dead body was carried hither and thither in frantic sorrow by her husband Siva. The mountain represented the body of Siva and when Sati’s genital organ fell on it, the mountain turned blue. The goddess herself is called Kamakhya, because she came there secretly to satisfy her amour (kama) with him. Thus the derivations of the K.P. make the mountain both a graveyard and a scene of the secret love-tryst of the goddess.

Variety of Names
Other variants of the name are Kama, Kamada, etc. The element-akhya often appears as a phonastic derivative after other less known names of the goddess, e.g. Sivakhya, Nadakhya, Brahmakhya, etc.–(Kurma Purana). Thus the goddess might be called either Kama or Kamakhya.
]]>
    </string>


    <string name="text14"> <![CDATA[
        Prayaga Madhaveswari is one of the 18 Shaktippethas. She is also called as Alopi mata / Lalita
Sthala Purana of Prayaga : Prayaga means Prakrishta Yaga, that means it is the place where Lord Brahma did a very great Yaga. Hence its name became Prayaga. Prayaga is considered as one of the Sapta mokshapuras. This place is also called as Theertharaj, that means king of all theerthas.  Another important point is, this is the place of Triveni Sangamam. Generally we consider the confluence of two water flows as a holy place. But, here we can see the confluence of three holy rivers, Ganges, Yamuna and Saraswati. All the three rivers have their importance individually. Hence the confluence became very very holy place. One should take a holy bath here when visited this place. Here Kumbhmela will be conducted for every 12 years.

Swami Brahmananda(Rakhal), first president of Ramakrishna math, spiritual son and one of the best student of Sri Ramakrishna paramahamsa, saw the goddess here as a small child with three Jatas. Trijata.
]]>
    </string>


    <string name="text15"> <![CDATA[
        Dedicated to Goddess Jwala Devi epitome of Shakti or Immense Power. Located at a distance of 34 kilometers to the south of Kangra in Himachal Pradesh. The temple was built by Raja Bhumi Chand Katoch. Jwala Devi is also referred to as the Flaming Goddess or the Jwalamukhi Devi

About Jwala Devi: The Jwala Devi is one of the most popular Hindu temples. It is situated on a small branch line on the Shimla to Dharamashala road and at a distance of twenty kilometers from the Jwalamukhi road. . The temple is in a town known as Jwalamukhi in Kangra district. This temple is visited by lakhs of devotees every year. Many curious people also visit this place to view the nine jwalas or flames that have been burning for centuries without any fuel. This temple also has a copper pipe through which natural gas is pushed out continuously.

The Jwala Devi Temple is one of the fifty one Shaktipeeths in India. The beautiful temple is set against a cliff. The dome of temple is aureate is of gold and has pinnacles. It also has a picturesque folding doorway of silver plate which was gifted by Sikh Raja Kharak Singh. The temple has an Indo-Sikh feel to it.
]]>
    </string>


    <string name="text16"> <![CDATA[
        The Mangla Gauri shrine in Gaya, one of the most holy sites has two rounded stones which symbolizes the breasts of the Goddess Sati, who is regarded as the first wife of Lord Shiva.

The Mangalagauri temple in Gaya (Bihar) has been mentioned in Padma Purana, Vayu Purana and Agni Purana and in other scriptures and tantric works. The present temple dates back to 1459 AD. The shrine is dedicated to Shakti or the mother Goddess in the predominantly Vaishnavite pilgrimage center of Gaya. Mangalagauri is worshiped as the Goddess of benevolence.

This temple constitutes an Upa-Shakti Pitha - where it is believed that a part of the body of Shakti fell - according to mythology. Here Shakti is worshiped in the form of a breast symbol, a symbol of nourishment.The temple is facing east, and is built on top of the Mangalagauri hill. A flight of steps and a motorable road lead to the temple. The sanctum houses the symbol of the Goddess and it also has some finely carved ancient relief sculptures.

The narrow by lanes with age old buildings, beautiful natural surroundings with rocky hills on the three sides and river flowing by the city on the western side makes the city look beautiful and elates the spiritual atmosphere of the place.

]]>
    </string>


    <string name="text17"> <![CDATA[
        The Karna kundala(Ear ring) of Devi fell here. Hence Devi Maa here is also known as Manikarni or Manikarnika. The Puranas say that this city exists even after the Pralaya. The famous place ‘Manikarnika’ is located here and named so because the earring of Goddess Sati was like a pearl (Mani). Goddess worshiped here as Maa Vishalakshi and Lord Shiva as Kala or Kaal Bhairva.

Some pundits feel that karna kundala is merely an ornament and not part of the body. Therefore this place can at best be considered as a upapeetha, a minor or sub-centre. Another version says that this is a shakti peetha only because one of the three eyes (Akshi) fell here. As the divine eye can perceive the entire universe, Mother here is called Vishalakshi, the vast-eyed. Vishalakshi Devi temple is a powerful Shakti Peeth and any pooja, charity, recitation of devi mantras performed in this premises is considered to yield very high results. Unmarried girls worshiping Vishalakshi Devi are sure to get married, childless couple will certainly be blessed with a child, even the most unfortunate ladies will find all fortunes coming their way.

visalakshi devi is present on the bank of the river Ganges.The temple is very small.An idol of Gauri is present in front of Visalakshi.
]]>
    </string>


    <string name="text18"> <![CDATA[
        Danteshwari Temple is temple dedicated to Goddess Danteshwari, and is one of the 18 Maha Shakti Peethas, shrines of Shakti, the divine feminine, spread across India. The temple built in 14th century by the Chalukyas of the South, is situated in Dantewada, a town situated 80 km from Jagdalpur Tehsil, Chattisgarh. Dantewada is named after the Goddess Danteshwari, the presiding deity of the earlier Kakatiya rulers. Traditionally she is the Kuldevi (family goddess) of Bastar state,

The temple is as according legends, the spot where the Daanth or Tooth of Sati fell, during the episode when all the Shakti shrines were created in the Satya Yuga.

Every year during Dusshera thousands of tribals from surrounding villages and jungles gather here to pay homage to the goddess, when her idol was taken out of that ancient Danteshwari temple and then taken around the city in an elaborate procession, now a popular tourist attraction part of the \'Bastar Dussehra\' festival.

]]>
    </string>


    <string name="text19"> <![CDATA[
        The temple is so vital to Kashmiris that Kashmiri language has the script of Sharda, which is little similar to Devanagari. Kalhana in Rajatarangini has said, devotees of Durga and Shiva from all over the country would flock to the temple of Sharda which can be approached from Bandipur in North Kashmir, about 80 km from Srinagar.

Through centuries the temple had remained the object of worship and devotion of lakhs of pilgrims from all over the country. Though in ruins now, the entire temple complex inspires grandeur and awe. The temple had a massive library attached to it which had priceless works on art, science, literature, architecture, music, humanities, medicine, astrology, astronomy, philosophy, law and jurisprudence and sanskrit etc. The library was used by scholars from even neighbouring countries.

Kashmir was also called "Shardapeeth" (the base of Sharda), the name being derived from the temple. We can take this to be an allegory of all the struggles Shankara had to face in his life. Ascending the seat of Sarvajna situated in Kashmir of the North is a symbol.
   ]]>
    </string>
</resources>
